{
  "reference_number": "2591",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It's critical we put in place a firm target now to start working towards if we want any chance of managing the transition process - the\n longer we leave planning, investing etc the steeper the cuts need to be and the harder to make them."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Zero needs to be zero, and even then the zero by 2050 target is based on only giving us a reasonable chance of avoiding truly\n\n catastrophic climate change impacts which we'll be inflicting on future generations."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should know by now that we can't buy our way out of our obligations. We need to be real and honest about our efforts."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If there is a global effort to move faster, spurred by the impacts of climate change appearing faster than is currently projected then we\n should definitely be able to speed up our reduction process and if by some incredibly slim chance there is something like massive\n\n volcanic activity which reduces solar radiation and we are just focused on staying fed we could adjust the target timing."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Five years seems like a reasonable amount of time to be planning and implementing."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "There should be no way for an opposition party to campaign on reducing any budget amount unless they will at least make that up in\n\n the subsequent five year block."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If there is something like massive volcanic emission of material such as sulphur dioxide into the upper atmosphere such that there is\n\nsignificant climate impact then we should be able to adapt to that."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And no opposition party should be able to campaign without firm plans on how they would achieve the emission budgets if they are\nproposing different action to the current government."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The actual hard reality of meeting those budget and how to be able to not just pick off the easier 'low hanging fruit' initially then stall."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Actual engineering/infrastructure construction/implementation experience not just political and management."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Adaptation is a separate issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think adaptation to climate change should be in a whole separate area as adaptation to the changing environment will need to cover\nother areas of degradation/change that stress our ability to maintain civilisation as we know it."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "While the 2050 date and the idea of staged five year emission budgets might convey a calm, considered process we need to keep in\nmind that right now in almost any given week in New Zealand we have housing, infrastructure and agricultural output being destroyed\n\nby weather related cold, drought, flooding and wind with invasive species being enabled and diseases spreading. What we might plan\nat our pace within our considerations of GDP and 'political reality' actually has no relation to the speed at which the climate is\nchanging and the impacts are appearing. To do anything less than put into legislation the most ambitious emissions reductions we\n\ncan is to lose any chance of getting ahead of the pace of the changes we've already started. We throw not only caution to the wind,\nbut the basis of our civilisation."
    }
  ]
}
